<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An Answer to the Desertion discuss'd</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 41 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A28554</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B3446</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R17941</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13165142</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13165142</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98221</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A28554)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98221)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 446:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An Answer to the Desertion discuss'd</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and sold by Rich. Janeway,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Jeremy Collier is the author of Desertion discuss'd.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Collier, Jeremy, 1650-1726.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Revolution of 1688 --  Sources.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:98221:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:98221:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>AN ANSWER TO THE DESERTION DISCUSS'D.</head>
            <p>IF many of our Long-Rob'd Divines, puft up with a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit of their own Parts, would but keep cloſer to their Texts, and their Duties, moſt certainly our Peace and Union would be much firmer, and more aſſured then it is. For being ſway'd by Intereſt and Profit, they are more afraid of loſing the Advantages of Earthly Preferment, then the Treaſures of Heavenly Felicity. Unleſs they ſwim in their own Wiſhes and Deſires, all Things are out of Order. The Church is in danger, they cry; here are <hi>Sharers</hi> coming in among Us: And by an odd kind of Eccleſiaſtical Policy, ſeem rather inclinable to return under the Yoke of Popery, then to endure the Equality of a Diſſenting Proteſtant; rather to be at the check of a Pope's Nuncio, then ſuffer the Fraternity of a Proteſtant Nonconformiſt. They ſaid nothing to the late King, till he began to touch their Copy-holds: then they call'd out for Help; and now they are angry with their Relief, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are afraid of well they know not what. And this is their Misfortune, that if all things anſwer not the full Height of their Expectations, they are the firſt that ſhould be laſt diſſatisfied. If all things go not well, as they imagine, they
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:98221:2"/>preſently grow moody and waſpiſh; and while they inſinuate their empty Notions into others, who admiring the fluency of their Pulpit Language, either out of Ignorance, or Lazineſs, allow them a Prerogative over their Underſtandings, the whole Nation muſt be embroyl'd by their Surmiſes and Miſtruſts.</p>
            <p>Elſe what had that Gentleman, who wrote the <hi>Deſertion Diſcuſs'd,</hi> to do to buſy his Brains with a <hi>Subject,</hi> neither ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaining to his Function, nor proper for his Talent? Why ſhould he be ſetting himſelf up againſt the voted Judgment of the chiefeſt and greateſt part of the Kingdom? A Man of his Profeſſion would have doubtleſs better employ'd himſelf, in contemplating the Story of the <hi>Three Murmurers</hi> againſt <hi>Moſes;</hi> and there have learn'd a more ſanctifi'd Leſſon, then to exalt his Sophiſtry againſt the Debates of a Solemn Aſſembly contriv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Publick Preſervation. For certainly never was a fairer Proſpect then now, ſince the many Revolutions under which the Britiſh Monarchy has labour'd, of its being reſtor'd to its ancient Grandeur and Renown, and of enjoying the Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages of Peace and Proſperity in a higher meaſure then ever. So that it muſt be look'd upon as the Effect, either of a moſt pernicious Malice, or a ſtrange diſtraction of Brain, for ſuch <hi>Diſcuſſers</hi> as theſe, to be throwing about the Darnel of their nice and froward Conceptions, on purpoſe to choak the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectations of ſo glorious a Harveſt. For they muſt be Men that want the government of right Reaſon within themſelves, as being enſlav'd either to vicious Cuſtom, or partial Affection, or elſe they would never run themſelves and others with ſo much precipitancy, into the ſhame and ignominy of upholding the ſubvertors of National Conſtitutions. And all this to blacken and defame the noble Endeavours, and prudent Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels of thoſe renowned Patriots that purſu'd the only means to reſcue a languiſhing Monarchy from impending Thraldom and Ruin.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>He does not wonder,</hi> he ſays, <hi>that a Man of ſo much ſenſe and integrity as his Friend is, ſhould be ſurprized at the Thrones being declared Vacant by the Lower Houſe of Convention. For how,</hi> ſays his Friend, <hi>can the Seat of the Government be empty, while the King, who all grant, had an unqueſtionable Title, is ſtill liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the <hi>Diſcuſſer</hi> here forgot, that it had been the reſolv'd
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:98221:2"/>Opinion of two Parliaments already, That there was no Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity for the Proteſtant Religion, the King's Life, or the eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh'd Government of the Kingdom, without paſſing a Bill for diſabling the Duke of <hi>York</hi> to inherit the Imperial Crown of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland;</hi> and that unleſs a Bill were paſs'd for excluding the Duke of <hi>York,</hi> the Houſe could not give any Supply to the King, without Danger to his Perſon, the Hazard of the Proteſtant Religion, and Breach of the Truſt in them repos'd by the People. Upon which a Bill did paſs the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, and was ſent up to the Lords for their Concurrence, by which <hi>James</hi> Duke of <hi>York</hi> was excluded and made for ever uncapable to Inherit, Poſſeſs or Enjoy the Imperial Crown of this Realm, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and he adjudg'd Guilty of High Treaſon, and to ſuffer the Pains and Penalties as in Caſe of High Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, if after ſuch a Time he ſhould claim, challenge, or at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt to poſſeſs or exerciſe any Authority or Juriſdiction, as King, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in any of the ſaid Dominions. 'Tis true, the Lords did not paſs this Bill, for Reaſons well known; yet was it ſuch a mutilation to the Duke's Title, to be diſabled from ſucceeding in the Kingdom, by the whole Body of the Commons, who are the Repreſentatives of the Nation, that it can never be ſaid, that all Men <hi>granted his Title unqueſtionable,</hi> as the <hi>Diſcuſſer</hi> impoſes upon the World. Beſides the many Inſtances in Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory, of ſeveral Princes who have forfeited their Succeſſion, and conſequently their Title to the Crown, for revolting from the Eſtabliſh'd Religion of the Realm.</p>
            <p>But, ſays the <hi>Diſcuſſer,</hi> for I look upon his Friend and Him to be all one; (and that he does but put the Queſtion with one ſide of his Mouth, and anſwer it with the other) <hi>I had thought our Laws, as well as our Religion, had been againſt the Depoſing Doctrine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That's not the Queſtion; but whether a Prince may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit thoſe Miſcarriages in Government, whether he may not ſo far, <hi>peccare in Leges &amp; Rempublicam,</hi> as to incur the Forfeiture of his Regal Power? and whether a Prince may be allow'd to ſubvert the ancient Conſtitutions and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion of a Nation, and yet be ſaid to be the Lawful King of that Realm? Theſe are the Queſtions: For then it is not the Law that depoſes him, nor the Religion that juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies it. But it is He that depoſes Himſelf: 'tis the bad Advice
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:98221:3"/>of Evil Counſellors to which he Liſtens, and which he follows to the ruin of the Kingdom, contrary to the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal Contract between Princes and People, grounded upon the Foundations of all Original Government; I ſay, 'tis that Adhering to Evil Counſel which depoſes a Prince by degrading him from a Lawful King to an Unlawful Tyrant, and fenders him Liable to the Animadverſion of the Law, and the impeachments of the oppreſs'd and injur'd People. To aſſert otherwiſe were to deprive all National Law and Religion of their ſelf Defence; which is againſt all the Law and Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the World. I am apt to believe that Chriſt himſelf had no very good Opinion of the lawfulneſs of <hi>Herod</hi>'s Regality, when he ſent him that Meſſage, <hi>Go tell that Fox, Herod:</hi> Which I look upon as a Depoſal and Degrading of that Arbitrary Prince by the Founder of our Religion, in his own Breaſt and Judgment, though he forbore the Execution of his Celeſtial Power. And therefore it is not the Error of Religion, but the Fault of thoſe that do not well diſtinguiſh, that Religion ſuffers in her Doctrines. For only he who governs according to Law is a King, he that endeavours to ſubvert the Law, is none. Nor is every rambling and precipitate Brain to be Judg of this neither, but the Solid Law, and fundamental Conſtitutions of the Realm. So that the Country Gentleman was miſtaken in his Thoughts, both of our Laws and our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. However the pretended Scrupulous Country-Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man deſires the <hi>Diſcuſſer to expound the State-Riddle of the Vacan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; and to give him the Ground of the late extraordinary Revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which the <hi>Diſcuſſer</hi> gives no direct anſwer at preſent, but deſires his Friend to take notice, <hi>That the Gentlemen of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention, who declar'd a Vacancy in the Government, lay'd the main Streſs of their opinion upon the King's withdrawing himſelf. For that ſince the Story of the French League, and the Buſineſs of the Prince of</hi> Wales <hi>were paſs'd over in ſilence, moſt Men believed that the pretended Breach of that which they called the Original Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract was no more then a popular Flouriſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All which is ſuch an imperfect peice of Incoherence, that none but a madman would have thruſt in by Head and Should<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, as the <hi>Diſcuſſer</hi> has done. For how can it be inferr'd that the <hi>Breach of the Original Contract,</hi> ſhould be a <hi>Popular
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:98221:3"/>Flouriſh,</hi> becauſe the Clandeſtin League, and the <hi>Falſe Birth</hi> are hitherto paſs'd over in ſilence? As for the <hi>ſurreptitious Birth,</hi> one would think it was ſufficiently dilated upon in the Declaration of the Lords; and why it is not farther brought upon the Stage, there may be ſeveral Reaſons given; and among the reſt, becauſe it may be thought that the Impoſture will vaniſh of it ſelf, and ſo there will be no need of caſting an Eternal Blot upon the memory of them that contriv'd and own'd it. Then for the Clandeſtin League, it Suffices that there is apparent Proof of it in Bank. But to call the Breach of the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginal Contract <hi>pretended,</hi> and a <hi>Popular Flouriſh,</hi> is a york of Malitious Reflection, which only ſerves to expoſe the <hi>Diſcuſſer</hi> to Publick cenſure. For as there is nothing more certain, then that there is an Original Contract between the King and People of <hi>England,</hi> the Breach of which has coſt the Effuſion of ſo much Blood; ſo is it as certain that that Original Contract was never ſo infallibly broken then it was of late. Which as it is allow'd by all the Laws of God and Man, to be a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient ground to ſeek a Remedy; ſo was nothing more vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly urg'd by the Convention. Which might have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinc'd the <hi>Diſcuſſer,</hi> that they did not pretend it for a popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Flouriſh.</p>
            <p>But now, leſt the Country Gentleman ſhould <hi>be ſhogg'd by ſeeing the Votes of ſo conſiderable a Meeting, debated by a private Hand;</hi> the <hi>Diſcuſſer</hi> reminds him, <hi>That a Parliament and a Convention are two different Things. The latter, for want of the King's Writs and Concurrence, having no ſhare in the Legiſlative Power.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the <hi>Diſcuſſer</hi> forgets, that it was only a Convention of Lords that ſent to <hi>Richard</hi> the Second to meet them at <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter;</hi> which the King at firſt promis'd to do; but upon altering his Mind, ſent him another peremptory Meſſage, that if he would not come according to his Promiſe, they would chuſe another King; and then proceeding farther, according to that Power they had, expell'd againſt the King's Will ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral of his chiefeſt Favourites from the Court; conſtrain'd o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to put in Sureties to appear at the next Parliament, and caus'd ſeveral others to be arreſted and committed to ſeveral Priſons. If a Convention could do this where the King was preſent, what ſignifi'd the Writs and Concurrence of an
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:98221:4"/>abſent Prince. Nor did they contend for Legiſlative Power, but only met in a kind of embodied Dictatorſhip to take care of the preſent Neceſſity of Affairs.</p>
            <p>But this, ſays the Diſcuſſer, was not juſtifiable, for that <hi>the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſity which they pretended, was either of their own making, or of their own ſubmitting to, which is the ſame Thing.</hi> But this is all Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence. For if the Neceſſity was of their own making, then were the Lords and Commons the Authors of all the Miſcarriages which they laid to the late King's Charge; If of their own ſubmitting to, then would they never have call'd out for ſuccour and crav'd Relief from their Oppreſſions. No— They were thoſe crying Grievan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſum'd up in the Declaration of the Lords Spiritual and Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral and Commons aſſembl'd at <hi>Weſtmiſter</hi> preſented to their Preſent Majeſties upon the Twelfth of February Laſt; which when the late King could not juſtify them by force of Arms, but fled for it, not being able to anſwer his endeavours to ſubvert and Extirpate the Proteſtant Religion and the Laws and Liberties of the Kingdom, put them to that neceſſity of aſſembling after an Unuſual Manner, to provide for the Common Safety.</p>
            <p>How ever the Diſcuſſer will have it a Neceſſity of their own creat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, tho never ſo falſe. <hi rend="margQuotes">For, ſays he, if the King had either not bin driven out of his Dominions, or invited back upon honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Terms, they needed not have had recourſe to ſuch unuſual ſingular Methods of proceeding.</hi> And thus the Diſcuſſer rambles out of one Untruth into another. For he fled from offer'd Treaty, forſook the defence of his own Forces, and left them to be disbanded in Arrears and without Payment; ſlipt from his own Council by Night, after he had appointed to meet them in Conſultation the next Morning. Nor could he juſtly ſuſpect, that any Violence would have been offer'd to Him in particular, being ſo well aſſur'd as he could not chooſe but be, of the Generous Inclination, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found Reſpect which the Prince had to his Perſon. But if the Guilt of peculiar Miſcarriages haſten'd his Departure, or overſway'd him to leave the Helm of Rule without any Form or Face of Government: That could ne're be call'd an Expulſion out of his Dominions. And therefore when a certain Gentleman waiting on him at <hi>Fever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſham</hi> beſought him to return to <hi>London,</hi> he gave the Perſon this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, <hi>That he was an honeſt Gentleman, but knew not what he knew.</hi> And when he had once abandon'd the Kingdom all forlorn without either Head or Conduct, without Council, or any Countenance of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:98221:4"/>Authority, then according to the Judgment of the Common-wealth of <hi>Venice</hi> in reference to the Succeſſion of <hi>Henry</hi> the 4th. it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long'd to the Nobility and chief Perſons of the Land, as they are the chief Defence of the Royal Authority, to take care of the Publick Safety, whether by uſual or unuſual Methods of proceeding it matters not; and they have both <hi>the Authority</hi> of Law and Neceſſity to juſtify their Proceedings.</p>
            <p>As for his being <hi>invited back upon Honourable Terms,</hi> 'tis well known how he return'd back, and went through the City on the Sunday Night, attended by his own Guards, and lodg'd in <hi>White-Hall,</hi> and this moſt certainly in order to an Accommodation. Only becauſe the Prince was coming to Town, he was ſent to, and for the avoiding any Diſturbance that might be prejudicial to his Perſon, was humbly deſir'd to retire to <hi>Ham</hi>-Houſe, with Liberty to make choice of what Perſon; he thought fit to attend him. Which he promiſed to do; but recollecting himſelf, and deſiring to know whether he might not return back to <hi>Rocheſter,</hi> word was ſent him the next Morning that he might do as he pleas'd. All this while here was no Conſtraint put upon him; ſo that he could not be ſaid to be driven out of his Dominions, but that it was his own Choice to forſake it.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding all this, The <hi>Diſcuſſer</hi> will undertake to prove, <hi rend="margQuotes">That the King before his withdrawing had ſufficient Grounds to make him apprehenſive of Danger, and therefore it could not be call'd an <hi>Abdication.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>But through the whole Purſuit of his Argument, the <hi>Diſcuſſer</hi> moſt wretchedly miſtakes the Point, quite miſtaking the Effects for the Cauſes. For, ſays he, <hi rend="margQuotes">Had not the King great Reaſon to retire to ſecure his Perſon and his Honour, when he had met with ſo many unfortunate Diſappointments, with ſo many ſurpriſing and unparallel'd Accidents? When part of the Army was revolted, and the Remainder too apparently unſerviceable; When the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple had ſuch fatal and unremoveable Prejudices againſt his Service? When there were ſuch terrible Diſorders in the Kingdom, and all Places were either flaming or ready to take Fire? What ſhould a Prince do when he had ſcarce any thing left him to loſe but him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, but conſult his Safety, and give way to the irreſiſtable Evil?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe are very great Diſappointments and evil Accidents indead to befal a Prince. But the <hi>Diſcuſſer</hi> forgets to tell ye, That the Prince
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:98221:5"/>brought all theſe Inconveniencies upon himſelf. The <hi>Diſcuſſer</hi> tells ye that part of the Army revolted, but he omits to tell ye, that it was out of a Generous Principle, for that being Proteſtants, they would not embrue their Hands in the Blood of their Fellow-Proteſtants and Countreymen, nor be Inſtruments to enſlave the Nation. He tells ye of terrible Diſorders in the Kingdom; but does not tell ye, it was time for the People to be in Diſorder, when they ſaw ſuch In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croachments upon their Ancient Franchiſes, ſuch Inundations of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery flowing in upon their Conſciences, and ſuch a rapid Violence of French Thraldom tumbling in upon their Necks. He complains that all Places were either flaming or ready to take Fire, but forgets to tell you who were the Incendiaries.</p>
            <p>Theſe therefore, with ſeveral others of the ſame Nature, being the true Cauſes that drew the foreſaid Inconveniencies upon the King, it follows, that tho the Secondary Conſtraint of his withdrawing might be occaſion'd by the Effects, yet the Primary Cauſe of his withdrawing proceeded from the Firſt Cauſes which produced the Effects. Conſequently ſuch a Retiring was voluntary and not forc'd; becauſe he may be juſtly ſaid to fly from ſomething of dreaded Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, rather then purſuing Danger, from which he was always at a diſtance far enough off, but dubious what would become of him as to the Former.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Diſcuſſer</hi> makes many other grievous Complaints to juſtify the King's Firſt withdrawing (for hitherto he is altogether upon that) but when he comes to ſum up all. <hi rend="margQuotes">In ſhort, ſays he, when the Forts and Revenue were thus diſpoſed of; when the Papiſts were to be disbanded, and the Proteſtants not to be truſted; when the Nation was under ſuch general and violent Diſſatisfactions; when the King in caſe of a Rupture had nothing upon the matter but his ſingle Perſon, to oppoſe againſt the Princes Arms, and thoſe of his Subjects; when his Mortal Enemies were to ſit Judges of his Crown and Dignity, if no farther; when Affairs were in this tempeſtuous Condition, to ſay that a Free and Indifferent Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment might be choſen, with the Relation to the King's Right as well as the People's, and that the King had no juſt viſible Cauſe to apprehend himſelf in Danger, is to out-face the Sun and trample upon the Underſtandings, and almoſt upon the Senſes of the whole Nation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for the Fortified Towns, it was but Reaſon that his then Highneſs the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> who came over to reſcue the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:98221:5"/>from Arbitrary Violence and Oppreſſion, ſhould demand them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> be put into his Power, well Knowing them to be then in the Hands of <hi>Iriſh</hi> Papiſts and Cut-Throats, of whom the People ſtood in Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual Fear, and who were rather a Conſternation then Security to the Kingdom. And the ſame reaſon holds in Relation to the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue. For all the World knows, what Vaſt Sums had been Squander'd away by the late King, when Duke, to keep off the ſitting of Parliaments, and to buy off the Members when they Sate; and when that Money was ſpent ſo much to the Detriment of the Realm, what Sollicitations were made to the French King for more, to carry on the Popiſh Cauſe and Intereſt. It was as well known how the Revenue had of late Years been Embezl'd to keep up a ſtanding Army of <hi>Iriſh</hi> Ragamuffins; as if <hi>England</hi> were now in its Turn to have been conquer'd by <hi>Ireland,</hi> as formerly <hi>Ireland</hi> had been conquer'd by <hi>England.</hi> From which fears when his preſent Majeſty had delivered the Nation, it was but reaſon that his Army ſhould be pay'd out of the Publick Stock for their happy Toyl and labour. For the Publick Revenue of all Kingdoms and States was ever Originally intended for the Preſervation, and not the Deſtruction of the People.</p>
            <p>Upon the Disbanding of the Papiſts, the <hi>Diſcuſſer</hi> makes a ſpecial Obſervation, <hi>That no Teſt-Acts nor any Others could barr the King from Liſting them as Common Souldiers.</hi> This perhaps may be true; that is to ſay, that a Proteſtant Prince may liſt Papiſts, and a Popiſh Prince Proteſtants, to follow him in a lawful War. But when a Popiſh Prince in a Proteſtant Nation had made his chiefeſt Levies of Popiſh Common Souldiers to over-aw his Proteſtant Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, and put his ſole Confidence in them for his known and open Deſigns and manifeſt Endeavors to introduce Popery into a Proteſtant Kingdom, contrary to the Law, 'twas time then to think of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banding ſuch Vermin, and ridding them out of the Land. And the reaſon why the Proteſtants could not be truſted was as certain. For if the King would not truſt his Proteſtants, nay diſarm'd them, when Papiſts were both arm'd and Employ'd, what reaſon had the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants to truſt the King. And this was that which among other Things created and foſter'd thoſe <hi>General and Violent Diſſatisfact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ions</hi> in the Nation. For Men have naturally a <hi>general</hi> and <hi>violent</hi> Antipathy againſt having their Throats Cut if they can help it. And therefore ſince the Kingdom by a Miraculous Providence had ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd its Redemption, 'tis to be wonder'd the Diſcuſſer ſhould i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magine
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:98221:6"/>'twas ever intended that the late K. ſhould be in a Condition again to oppoſe either his own or the perſons of any others againſt the Arms of the Prince or thoſe of his own Subjects. And whereas, he ſays, that the King's Mortal Enemies were to be the Judges of his Crown and Dignity, the Diſcuſſer ſhould have done well before he had made his Reflection upon ſo many Eminent Patriots, to have conſulted <hi>Grotius, l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 4, <hi>Par.</hi> 8. and the Example of <hi>Pauſamias</hi> King of <hi>Lacedaemon</hi> there cited. Certainly there was no ſuch Impoſſibility but that a Free and Indifferent Parliament might have been choſen to deal equally between the King and the People. For tho the King perhaps might be conſcious that he could not ſo well rely upon the Kindneſs of thoſe to whom he had always had ſuch an inveterate Antipathy, yet he might have rely'd upon the Juſtice of ſo many Great and Worthy Perſonages. So that it is the Diſcuſſer himſelf who out-faces the Sun and tramples upon the Underſtandings and Senſes of the whole Nation, who makes theſe little Rhetorical Flouriſhes to palliate and obſcure the Truth, and to inſinuate among the People, as if Wrong and Injuſtice had been done, where nothing was acted but what was a due debt to Self-Preſervation. And with the ſame Brazening the Diſcuſſer out-faces the Sun, and tramples up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Senſes of the Nation, to aſſert that a Deſertion of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, after ſuch Propoſals, which were rather Aſſurances of his Safety, was no Deſertion. He had been ſafer in the Affection of the People, when all his evil Counſellers had been remov'd from about him; he had been ſafer from the Importunities of his Prieſts and Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites; He had been more ſecure from running himſelf into farther danger, and ſafer in the Enjoyment of his Royal Dignity. But he who had ſo Solemnly ſworn to Eſtabliſh Popery in <hi>England</hi> or die in the Attempt, though himſelf no where ſafe perhapps, but where he might be procuring his future Bliſs, by the Performance of his Vow.</p>
            <p>The Diſcuſſer now advances to the King's ſecond withdrawing, and puts the Queſtion, <hi>what the King had done to incur a forfeiture by his firſt Retirement?</hi> Indeed what had he not done? If the <hi>Diſcuſſer</hi> forgot in his Diſcuſſing Heat, the <hi>Declaration</hi> preſented to their Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Majeſties would have rubb'd up his Memory. Among the reſt there was one, <hi>That he had endeavoured to Subvert and Extirpate the Proteſtant Religion, and the Laws and Liberties of the Kingdom, by raiſing and keeping a Standing Army in the Kingdom in time of Peace, without Conſent of Parliament, and quartering Souldiers con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:98221:6"/>to Law; and by cauſing ſeveral of his good Subjects to be Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>'d at the ſame time when Papiſts were both Arm'd and Employ'd.</hi> Now to what purpoſe was all this, but to Subject the Kingdom to the Tyranny of the Pope? In ſuch a caſe <hi>Bartl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y</hi> cited by <hi>Gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 4. <hi>per.</hi> 10. gives this for his Opinion, <hi>Si Rex reguum alienet, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> alij Subjici<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t, amitti ab <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o Regnum.</hi> To which <hi>Grotius</hi> himſelf adds, <hi>Si Rex reipſa tradere regnum aut Subjicers molliatur, quin ei r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fiſti in hoc p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſe non dubit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Ali<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d eſt en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n Imperiu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, ali<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d hab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ndi modus; qui no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, obſtar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>teſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>op<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After all this, it cannot be imagin'd that the King returned the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond time <hi>with an intention is govern;</hi> unleſs he might govern at his own will and Pleaſure as he did before. But that would not be ſuff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r'd him; for they who had now avoided the Yoke ſo near putting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout their Necks, would never endure it ſhould come ſo near their ſhoulders again. Therefore all the Probality in the World is on this ſide, That the King perceiving, that by taking the Goverment up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him again, he ſhould not be able to attain thoſe Ends which he had made the Buſineſs of his whole Reign; reſolv'd to relinquiſh it altogether. At which time being at liberty to go or ſtay, his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture muſt of neceſſity be accounted Voluntary, and conſequently an Abſolute <hi>Abdication.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, it is impoſſible that the King could be frighted out of his Dominions, by the making of two or three Addreſſes to his then Royal Highneſs the Prince of <hi>Orange;</hi> for it was no more than rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onally he could expect would be done; more eſpecially from the <hi>City</hi> to the Perſon, who next under God had deliver'd them from their Continual fears of Fire and Sword. Nor by the denying him a little Gold to <hi>Heal</hi> with; which looks like an improbable Story of the Diſcuſſer's own framing. Theſe are Motions ſo inconſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for a King to forſake his Dominions, that the Diſcuſſer ſeems to have Conjur'd them up meerly to degrade the Courage of the Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting Monarch, and to mortify his own Diſcuſſion. But after all, the Queſtion may be fairly put, whether <hi>Withdrawing,</hi> in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of our Law, does not rather imply a Guilt, than an Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of Danger, unleſs it be that of being call'd to an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, ſince the Query always propounded to the Jury is, <hi>Did he fly for't?</hi> Which indeed ought to be the Legal Determination of this Diſpute.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:98221:7"/>
            <p>However the <hi>Diſouſſer</hi> goes on, and tells us, <hi>We are to obſerve, that to abdicate an Office always ſuppoſes the Conſent of him who quits.</hi> And this he affirms to be the meaning of the Word out of <hi>Saluſt, Tully, Livy</hi> and <hi>Grotius.</hi> But both the Suppoſal, and the Aſſeveration are falſe. For <hi>Conſent</hi> implies, that the Queſtion muſt be put, Whether the Perſon will Abdicate or no? Which never was put to any Abdicator in this World. Upon a forc'd Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignation it has. But a forc'd Reſignation is no Abdication. Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it is that <hi>Abdicar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> ſignifies to <hi>renounce, forgoe,</hi> or <hi>abandon.</hi> And the Motives to this Abdication are various, and generally pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing upon the Reaſon of the Perſon that Abdicates himſelf, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Condition of Affairs and the Circumſtances he is under. And therefore tho a Magiſtrate may abdicate with the conſent of others, yet he rarely does it out of a natural Inclination. Thus it cannot be imagined that <hi>Lentulus,</hi> one of the Conſpirators with <hi>Catiline,</hi> abdicated the Pretorſhip, with the Conſent of his own Will, for he was one of the moſt aſpiring Men in the Univerſe; but becauſe he found himſelf ſo obnoxious that he could hold it no longer: Thus <hi>Sylla</hi> abdicated the Dictatorſhip out of a Vain-glorious Opinion of Felicity that attended him, and to ſhew that he had ſuch an awe over the <hi>Romans,</hi> that tho he were a Private Perſon, no body durſt call him to an Account for the Cruelties he had committed. Hiſtory tells us, that <hi>Diocleſian</hi> abdicated the Empire, for madneſs that he could not have his Will of the Chriſtians. How does the <hi>Diſcuſſer</hi> know, but that King <hi>James</hi> abdicated the Government becauſe he could not have his Will of the Proteſtants? <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>Vth</hi> abdicated the Empire, becauſe he found his wonted Good For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune had left him. <hi>Bernard Rasfield</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Munſter</hi> finding himſelf between two Grindſtones, the Perſecution of the <hi>German</hi> Prieſts, for going about to deprive them of their Concubines, and the Pope's Excommunication, if he did it not; abdicated his Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pality and Biſhoprick, that he might be at quiet. Laſtly, to ſhew that Abdication does not <hi>always</hi> imply Conſent, <hi>Brutus</hi> compell'd <hi>Tarquinius Collatinus</hi> to abdicate the Conſulſhip, only becauſe his <hi>Praenomen</hi> was <hi>inviſum Civitati.</hi> And then as for what the Diſcuſſer adds out of <hi>Grotius, That a Neglect or Omiſſion in the Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Government, is by no means to be interpreted a Renunciation of it;</hi> there's no Body cenſures the late King for any Omiſſion or want of Diligence in the Adminiſtration of his Government, for he
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:98221:7"/>was too diligent indeed; and that Diligence was the main Grievance which diſguſted the People; his Diligence to extirpate the Proteſtant Religion; his Diligence to ſubvert the Laws and Liberties of the Kingdom; and his Diligence to introduce Popery. And this Dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, 'tis to be fear'd, was one of the main Cauſes of his Abdica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: Had he omitted more, he would have had leſs reaſon to have abdicated. And therefore it is a Vanity to infer that there can be no Preten<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e for an <hi>Abdication,</hi> becauſe the Word, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> he ſays, <hi>always,</hi> that is very rarely, or never, ſuppoſes the <hi>Conſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt</hi> of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> that quits.</hi> For that it is not in the Na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ure of M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n to abdicate Empires, King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, Wealth and Honours, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ore m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt be ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e compulſive Reaſon within that moves them to it. When Princes find the Times and Conſtitutions of the Kingdom will not bear th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ir Government; when Emperors grow ſtiff and ſtark with Age, and beg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n to feel the Laſhes of ill-Fortune; when Ambitious Aſpirers perceive they muſt take other Meaſures to compaſs their Deſigns, then they ſwallow a ſelf-denying Ordinance, and think it convenient to retire from the Cares of the World, or out of Harms way.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Diſcuſſer</hi> ſays, <hi>We have but two Inſtances with us which look like an Abdication ſince the Conqueſt,</hi> which are in the Reigns of <hi>Edward</hi> II. and <hi>Richard</hi> II. <hi>both which were unjuſtly depos'd by their Subjects.</hi> 'Tis true, they were ſo far from looking like Abdications, that they were no Abdications at all. For both thoſe Princes being under a ſtrict Confinement, it was impoſſible for them to <hi>abdicate,</hi> unleſs they could have made their Eſcapes. Therefore they were forc'd Reſignations, and conſequently formal Depoſals. Nor had the Queen of <hi>Henry</hi> of <hi>Lancaſter</hi> any cauſe to declare the Throne Vacant, as having already taken care to fill it themſelves: And whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thoſe Princes would have reſign'd or no, it would have ſignified little to them that were by Claim in Poſſeſſion. But the <hi>Diſcuſſer</hi> has overſlipp'd one Inſtance of a Perfect <hi>Abdication</hi> ſince the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, which the King would have certainly felt to his Coſt, had not the Pope and the <hi>Poictovins</hi> been his true Friends: and the Caſe was much the ſame as at this Time. For the Lords and Barons of the Realm in the Reign of King <hi>John,</hi> having often deſired the King to reſtore them their Ancient Rights and Liberties, and finding nothing but Deluſions, reſolve no longer to be abus'd but betake themſelves to Arms. The King then lying at <hi>Windſor;</hi> and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:98221:8"/>himſelf too weak for the Lords, thought it no good way to proceed by Force but rather by Fraud, and therefore ſends to the Lords, that if they would come to <hi>Windſor</hi> he would grant their Demands. Thither the Lords repairing, tho in a Military Manner (for they durſt not truſt the King's Word) he ſaluted them all kindly, and promis'd to give them Satisfaction in all they demanded: And to that Purpoſe in a Meadow between <hi>Stains</hi> and <hi>Windſor,</hi> call'd <hi>Running-Mead,</hi> he freely conſented to confirm their former Charters; and was content that ſome Grave Perſonages ſhould be made choice of to ſee it confirm'd. But the next Day, when it was to be done, he withdraws himſelf privately to <hi>South-Hampton,</hi> and thence to the Iſle of <hi>Wight:</hi> Where it was concluded that he ſhould ſend to the Pope, acquaint him with the Mutiny of his Lords, and require his Holineſſes help. In the mean time the King lay ſculking up and down for three Months together in Corners, that no Body knew where to find him; or which was worſe, as ſome write; roving and practiſing Pyracy upon the Neighbouring Seas.</p>
            <p>Whether the Lords and Barons did in Words declare this to be a Vacancy of the Throne, is not material to enquire. Perhaps they were not ſo curious in thoſe Days: But what they did in Deeds, amounted to the ſame as if they had done it in Words. For percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving themſelves thus eluded, they ſwore upon the Holy Altar to be reveng'd. And what Revenge that was likely to have been is eaſy to conjecture, by their ſwearing Allegiance afterwards to <hi>Lewis</hi> the French King's Son, and bearing Fealty to him till the Death of the King. Whence it may be inferr'd, That if a Prince in Hoſtility with his Subjects deſerts his Kingdom, upon any Account, They who are next to the Government are not to heſitate as King <hi>John</hi>'s Barons did, in expectation of the King's Return, but immediately to take care of the Common Safety, leſt they ſhould bring the ſame Ruin upon the Kingdom, as thoſe Barons did by their Delay.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, If the <hi>Diſcuſſer</hi> will not be convinc'd by what has hitherto been ſaid, Let him examine the King's own words, and try whether he can pick out any better Conſtruction out of them then that which I ſhall make.</p>
            <p>Says the late King in his Letter to the Earl of <hi>Feverſham, Things being come to that Extremity, that I have been forc'd to ſend away the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:98221:8"/>Queen, and my Son the Prince of</hi> Wales, <hi>that they might was fall into my Enemies hands, I am oblig'd to do the ſame thing, and to endeavour no ſecure my ſelf the beſt I can, &amp;c.</hi> Expreſſions of a diſponding Mind, and only full of Grief for the Diſappointment of the Popiſh Career. The King was afraid of the Queen, and his Son the Prince of <hi>Wales</hi> as he calls him, and therefore deeming if convenient to ſend Them out of the way, believes himſelf oblig'd to follow them. 'Tis true, there might be ſome Reaſon perhaps for him to ſend Them away; but none to ſend away himſelf, not being under the ſame Circumſtances. For let it be Paternal or Conjugal Affection, or both together; What could be a greater Deſertion than this, for the ſake of a Wife and a Son to leave three Kingdoms at ſix and ſevens? He ſpeaks of <hi>ſecuring himſelf as well as he can,</hi> but mentions nothing of Danger; only leaves it to the Lord <hi>Feverſham</hi> and others to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume the Cauſes of his Fears. But certainly the apprehenſion of Danger can never excuſe a Sovereign Magiſtrate from the Deſertion of his Dominions, at the ſame time ſtriving and ſtrugling under the Pangs of the Diſſolution of Government. If ſuch a Deſertion of his Territories in that forlorn and languiſhing Condition, to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany the Tribulations of a Wife and a Son, be not a perfect Abdica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Territories, the Words <hi>relinquiſh, deſert, forgo, aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, abdicate,</hi> have loſt their Signification. Thus <hi>Lyſimachus</hi> in <hi>Plutarch, de ſera vindicta Dei,</hi> after he had ſurrendered his Perſon and Dominions to the <hi>Getae,</hi> for a Draught of Drink, in the extro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of a parching Thirſt, when he had quench'd his Thirſt cryed out, <hi>O pravum Hominem!</hi> that for ſo ſmall a Pleaſure have loſt ſo great a Kingdom. He would be thought very unfit to be the Maſter of a Ship, that ſhould throw himſelf into the Sea, when his Veſſel and Cargoe were almoſt ready to periſh. And I will appeal to the Lord of <hi>Wemm</hi> himſelf, whether if he went to try an Abdicating Prince upon this Point, with the ſame Huffing and Domineering as he did Inferiour Offenders, he would take it for a good Juſtification to ſay, I had thought, or I apprehended my Perſon to be in Danger. Rather it becomes a Prince at ſuch a time to exert his Courage, and contemn his own, when the publick Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity lies at Stake, eſpecially when the Remedy propounded was ſo eaſy as the Convoking of a Free Parliament. But to withdraw at ſuch a perillous Conjuncture from the Application of his deſir'd, nay
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:98221:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>almoſt implor'd <hi>Aſſiſtance;</hi> What can the <hi>Diſcuſſer</hi> think of himſelf to deny ſo plain an <hi>Abdication?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this I take to be the Opinion of the late King's Abdication, intimated by the Lords Spiritual and Temporal aſſembled at <hi>Guild-Hall,</hi> Decemb. 1688. where they are pleaſed to ſay, <hi>That they did reaſonably hope that the King having ſent forth his Proclamation and Writs for a free Parliament, they might have reſted ſecure</hi> (as doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs the King might alſo have done) <hi>in that Meeting. But his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty having withdrawn himſelf,</hi> &amp;c. they did therefore <hi>unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly reſolve to apply themſelves to his Highneſs the</hi> Prince of <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>range,</hi> &amp;c. That is to ſay, The King having withdrawn himſelf from the Cure of the Grand Diſtempers of the Nation, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently Abdicated the Government, they reſolv'd to apply themſelves to a more Skilful, at leaſt a more Willing Phyſician. Which had the Diſcuſſer more conſiderately diſcuſs'd, when he wrote his Diſcuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, would have ſav'd him a great deal of trouble and expence.</p>
            <p>Thus much for the Reaſons which the Diſcuſſer brings to prove that the King, before his withdrawing, had ſufficient Grounds to make him apprehenſive of Danger, and that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it cannot be call'd an <hi>Abdication.</hi> That which follows, being altogether grounded upon certain Statutes and Laws of the Land, to the knowledg of which the Diſcuſſer ſeems to be a great Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tender, is anſwer'd in a Word, That they who pronounc'd the Throne Vacant, underſtood the Latitude of their Power, and the Intent and Limits of the Laws and Statutes of this Realm to that Degree, that if nothing elſe, the Conſideration of that might have deterr'd the Diſcuſſer from the Preſumption of appearing ſo vainly and ſcandalouſly in the World. Nor would I be thought ſo impertinent to tranſgreſs the Bounds of my own Underſtanding as he has done. For indeed, to tell ye the Truth, if the Diſcuſſer ſhould come to a Trial at <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall,</hi> I am afraid the Lawyers will certainly inform him that he has very much either miſtaken or miſquoted his Authors.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>London</hi> printed, and ſold by <hi>Rich. Janeway,</hi> 1689.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:98221:9"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
